Reproductive confusion, or the benefits of not knowing when
leeminlinh Rối loạn sinh sản hay những lợi ích của việc không biết khi nào
to have sex, Getting help with childcare, passing your baby
quan hệ tình dục, nhận sự giúp đỡ với việc chăm sóc con cái, chuyền con bạn
around to other adults, isn't possible unless a mother has
sang tay người lớn khác, là không thể trừ phi một người mẹ
real good confidence in the adults around her.
thực sự tin vào những người lớn xung quanh cô.
If a rival female might kill it, or if a male might neglect
nếu một người phụ nữ tình địch khác giết đứa con, hoặc một người mẹ sao nhãng con mình
it, well, it's just not possible to do alloparenting.
vấn đề này không thể chỉ đơn giản là việc đưa đứa bé cho những người khác nuôi dưỡng .
Our nearest relatives aren't very good at socially
Những người họ hàng gần nhất không giỏi lắm trong việc hợp tác
cooperating to raise infants.
để nuôi lớn đứa bé.
In fact, chimpanzees, for example, have trouble sharing
Ví dụ, trong thực tế loài tinh tinh gặp rắc rối với việc chia sẻ
food with their own children, let alone with
thức ăn cho các con của chúng, bỏ mặc
somebody else's children.
con của những con khác.
However, there are primates that do cooperatively parent,
Tuy nhiên, có một số loài động vật linh trưởng có thể làm bố mẹ cộng tác được,
and they're much better at sharing.
và chúng còn làm tốt hơn khi chia xẻ với nhau.
We know, for example, human foragers, are very good at
Chúng ta được biết, loài người ở thời kỳ hái lượm rất thành thạo trong việc
sharing food with an entire group or tribe.
chia sẻ thức ăn với cả một nhóm hoặc bộ lạc.
Cooperative parenting allowed our infants to
Nuôi nấng con cái hợp tác làm cho
grow up more slowly.
những đứa trẻ chậm lớn hơn.
It provided the mother with more support to keep the
Nuôi con hợp tác cung cấp cho người mẹ nguồn thức ăn dự trữ
infant provisioned as it grew into childhood.
từ khi đứa trẻ còn sơ sinh đến khi nó lớn.
But it also allowed the mothers to go back into the
Điều đó còn cho phép người mẹ
reproductive pool more quickly than their children became
phục hồi khả năng sinh sản nhanh hơn
independent.
khi những đứa trẻ đã có thể tự lập.
This allowed that developmental window, that
Điều này cho phép cánh cửa phát triển, là khoảng thời gian những đứa trẻ
time when children are growing so rapidly and their brains
đang trưởng thành thật nhanh và
are developing to extend and actually become longer.
não bộ của chúng đang phát triển bị kéo dài và thật sự trở nên lâu dài hơn.
Without this change in reproduction, we wouldn't be
Nếu không có sự thay đổi này trong quá trình sinh sản
able to learn as much as we do, we wouldn't be able to
chúng ta sẽ không thể học hỏi nhiều như chúng ta bây giờ
develop our brains the way we do, we wouldn't have the
chúng ta không thể phát triển não bộ theo cách của chúng ta bây giờ
technology that we have.
chúng ta sẽ không thể có kỹ thuật mà chúng ta có.
The change in reproduction was a precondition for developing
Sự thay đổi trong quá trình sinh sản là một điều kiện tiên quyết
our human way of life.
cho sự phát triển lối sống của loài người.
But our ancestors didn't know they were doing this.
Nhưng tổ tiên của chúng ta không biết họ đã làm điều đó.
They were completely unaware that there was this long, slow
Họ hoàn toàn không ý thức rằng
sexual revolution happening.
có một cuộc cách mạng giới tính đang chậm rãi diễn ra.
They didn't know what they were doing.
Họ đã không biết họ đang làm gì.
One of the most productive forms of confusion that humans
Một trong những hình thái sinh sản mơ hồ
have developed is that we do not know when we are
mà loài người phát triển là ta không biết
reproductively viable.
khi nào chúng ta tồn tại khả năng sinh sản.
We don't know when to have sex.
Ta không biết khi nào có sự giao hợp.
I live on a farm with horses and nothing could be clearer
Ta sống ở một nông trại với bầy ngựa và không có gì rõ ràng hơn
to a horse than when a mare is fertile.
trong đám ngựa khi mà một con cái vào thời kỳ sinh sản.
In fact, kind of all hell breaks lose.
Thực tế, như một trận hỗn loạn vậy.
The stallions are nuts, even the geldings get excited, and
Đám ngựa dở hơi, ngay cả đám ngựa thiến cũng trở nên hưng phấn
they've got to do.
và chắc chắn chúng sẽ như thế.
But even the mares themselves, they start to fight more than
Mà ngay cả bản thân những con cái cũng đánh nhau thường xuyên
usual, they'll spray each other with a kind of pheromone
chúng phun vào nhau một loại pheromone
laced urine, which all signals when they're
trong nước tiểu, dấu hiệu
reproductively viable.
khi chúng bước vào thời kỳ sinh sản.
If you actually let a stallion into a paddock with a mare in
Nếu ta thực sự để một con ngựa đực vào một bãi cỏ vói một con ngựa cái như vậy
heat, it's complete chaos.
mọi thứ sẽ hoàn toàn hỗn loạn.
Nothing else will matter to the two of them except
Không có gì ảnh hưởng được đến hai bọn chúng
deciding whether they're going to mate until
trừ việc để bọn chúng kết đôi
they settle the question.
cho đến khi chúng giải quyết được vấn đề.
In many species, mating is like this.
Ở nhiều loài, kết đôi đều là như vậy.
The females, they signal when they're fertile.
Những con cái, chúng có dấu hiệu khi có khả năng sinh sản.
They go through something we called estrus.
Chúng trải qua một thứ mà chúng ta gọi là thời kỳ động đực
This makes mating a compulsory affair, even a kind of
Điều này làm cho việc kết đôi trở thành một công việc bắt buộc
temporary insanity.
đại loại như là một tình trạng mất kiểm soát tạm thời.
In humans, it's not obvious.
Ở loài người, chuyện đó không rõ ràng như vậy.
Females don't signal very clearly when they're
Phụ nữ không có dấu hiệu rõ ràng khi họ rụng trứng,
ovulating, when they're most fertile.
khi họ đang có khả năng sinh sản nhất.
In fact, in many cases, we have no idea what's going on.
Trong thực tế, nhiều trường hợp ta không biết chuyện gì đang xảy ra.
This can make women slightly different during their period
chuyện đó có thể khiến phụ nữ khác đi một chút trong chu kỳ tháng của họ
of the month when they're fertile, but for the most
khi họ đang rụng trứng
part, I think the real takeaway is that humans are
nhưng phần lớn theo tôi là loài người
concealing their estrus.
đang giấu diếm thời kỳ rụng trứng của họ.
They have concealed their fertility.
họ giấu diếm khả năng sinh sản.
We can go through a day completely oblivious to
Chúng ta có thể trải qua những ngày hoàn toàn lãng quên
whether the woman sitting alongside us in a cafe is
về chuyện người phụ nữ ngồi cạnh chúng ta trong một tiệm cafe
fertile or not.
có đang trong thời kỳ rụng trứng hay không..
I can even have a lecture with hundreds of students in it,
Chúng ta có thể thuyết trình với hàng trăm sinh viên,
and nobody is signalling to the other students that
và không ai tỏ vẻ với những người khác
they've got an egg ready to fertilise.
rằng trứng của họ đang sẵn sàng thụ tinh.
We're not the only species does this, but given our
Chúng ta không phải là loài duy nhất như vậy,
intelligence and our perceptiveness, the degree to
nhưng với trí tuệ và khả năng quan sát của chúng ta
which we conceal estrus, we conceal fertility from
trình độ mà chúng ta giấu diếm thời kỳ rụng trứng, chúng ta giấu diếm khả năng sinh sản với chính đồng loại,
ourselves, would seem to be maladaptive, unless something
có vẻ như là một sự thích nghi không tốt
else is going on.
trừ khi có thứ gì khác đang xảy ra.
The first thing to notice about concealed estrus is it
Điều cần lưu ý đầu tiên về việc giấu diếm này ở loài người
in humans, females don't really need to signal when
là phụ nữ không thực sự cần phải ra dấu hiệu
they're fertile for males to be interested in them.
khi họ rụng trứng để thu hút sự chú ý của đàn ông.
In some species, the males can be genuinely ambivalent about
Ở một số loài, giống đực có thể có mâu thuẫn
the presence of females, except during that time of the
về sự có mặt của giống cái, trừ khi
month when the females are signalling
giống cái đang ở trong giai đoạn
that they're fertile.
có dấu hiệu có khả năng sinh sản.
The same thing is true for human women, too.
Điều này cũng tương tự đối với loài người.
Just like men, they don't need to be drunk on pheromones to
Như đàn ông không cần phải bị quyến rũ bởi pheromones
be interested in sex.
thì mới có hứng thú với sex.
This isn't the case with all species.
Không phải loài nào cũng như vậy.
This kind of readiness for sex may have acted as a kind of
Tình trạng sẵn sàng cho sex có thể xem như là
social glue.
một loại hành động kết nối xã hội.
That is, males may have had a more successful time
Có nghĩa là, giống đực có thể có khả năng sinh sản thành công nhiều hơn
reproducing if they stuck around the females.
khi giống đực quanh quẩn gần giống cái.
First, to make sure that the females didn't mate with
Thứ nhất, phải đảm bảo rằng giống cái không kết đôi với giống đực khác
another male when they were fertile, but also perhaps even
khi giống cái đang trong thời kỳ sinh sản
to share in the parenting.
và ngay cả khi đang nuôi con hợp tác.
Although remember, the mothers had other alloparents, so they
mặc dù phải nhớ rằng, những con mẹ nuôi con có sự hỗ trợ của những con khác
didn't have to have males.
nên không cần phải có giống đực.
The third thing is estrus has a cost.
Điều thứ ba là thời kỳ rụng trứng cũng có cái giá của nó.
In those species that have it, the metabolic cost of
In those species that have it, the metabolic cost of
maintaining a large swelling, the danger that you have,
maintaining a large swelling, the danger that you have,
getting extra diseases or infections, you
getting extra diseases or infections, you
pay a price for it.
pay a price for it.
So if you don't need it in some cases, evolution might
So if you don't need it in some cases, evolution might
actually make sense for it to get rid of it.
actually make sense for it to get rid of it.
Finally, concealing estrus may have also
Finally, concealing estrus may have also
helped to confuse paternity.
helped to confuse paternity.
And if females were using concealing paternity to
And if females were using concealing paternity to
protect their infants from the chance that a male might
protect their infants from the chance that a male might
actually kill it, well this would be a further insurance.
actually kill it, well this would be a further insurance.
Concealing estrus would confuse the potential fathers
Concealing estrus would confuse the potential fathers
about who was actually the father of a child.
about who was actually the father of a child.
Concealing estrus, however, had other social effects.
Concealing estrus, however, had other social effects.
During female fertility in the kinds of species that have
During female fertility in the kinds of species that have
estrus, it can be a pretty rough time.
estrus, it can be a pretty rough time.
Males fight with males for dominance and for access to
Males fight with males for dominance and for access to
females, males bully females sometimes, trying to isolate
females, males bully females sometimes, trying to isolate
them from other males, or keep them out of the group.
them from other males, or keep them out of the group.
It can be a pretty rough time to interact socially.
It can be a pretty rough time to interact socially.
By concealing estrus, it may have made it possible for
By concealing estrus, it may have made it possible for
humans to spend more time together.
humans to spend more time together.
With estrus, it's not just that the lady next to its got
With estrus, it's not just that the lady next to its got
swollen buttocks, or she's changed colours, or she's
swollen buttocks, or she's changed colours, or she's
pumping out pheromones.
pumping out pheromones.
It's what that estrus does to the whole group.
It's what that estrus does to the whole group.
In contrast, humans can gather in large numbers without the
In contrast, humans can gather in large numbers without the
males fighting over the ovulating females, if you know
males fighting over the ovulating females, if you know
what I mean.
what I mean.
We can tell when we compare ourselves to our closest
We can tell when we compare ourselves to our closest
relative, to the chimpanzees and gorillas, that we haven't
relative, to the chimpanzees and gorillas, that we haven't
been reproducing, and our ancestors haven't been
been reproducing, and our ancestors haven't been
reproducing like them for millions of years.
reproducing like them for millions of years.
We have the evidence of this long, slow sexual revolution,
We have the evidence of this long, slow sexual revolution,
how the needs of our babies, their extreme altricial
how the needs of our babies, their extreme altricial
nature, has actually shaped us to keep them alive, these
nature, has actually shaped us to keep them alive, these
fragile babies.
fragile babies.
And the way that we took care of them, and the way that they
And the way that we took care of them, and the way that they
asked us for our support, has shaped our social skills and
asked us for our support, has shaped our social skills and
developed our social intelligence to
developed our social intelligence to
unprecedented levels.
unprecedented levels.
In this way, our babies made us human.
In this way, our babies made us human.
Our next topic is sexuality.
Our next topic is sexuality.
Because it's just not natural.
Because it's just not natural.